Guide to the French transvestite postcards, circa 1900-1930.
French transvestite postcards
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
French transvestite postcards, circa 1900-1925.
7778
Gerard Koskovich, collector
204 items.
Photographs, Postcards
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Postcards portraying cross-dressing and female and male impersonators in France.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Postcards portraying cross-dressing and female and male impersonators in France, both real-photo postcards, some hand-colored, and those printed using heliogravure and offset methods. All are printed between circa 1900 and 1925 in France, except for four printed in other European countries, and all the performers appeared in France. Many images are photographs of performers on amateur, café-concert, music-hall, and legitimate stages at the high-point of cross-dressing as a form of entertainment in France.
In one postcard, Jeanne Bloch is imitating Armand Fallières, President of the French Republic, 1906-1913, a provocative statement at a time when French women were still denied the right to vote. Eleven portray Robert Bertin, one of the leading female impersonators of the Belle Epoque, including images of his expert imitations of the famous singer Yvette Guilbert, who appeared in the paintings of Henri Toulouse-Lautrec, and the dancer Polaire, a lover of novelist Colette. Gerard Koskovich notes that "in the period before World War I, Bertin toured extensively, appearing not only in Paris and the provinces but also in such distant places as Buenos Aires,"and that Eloi Ouvrard, another noted music-hall performer of the era, singled out Bertin for particular praise: "Dès qu'il nous présentait une des étoiles féminines, on avait l'impression d'admirer en scène, non seulement une vraie femme mais bien une superbe et jolie femme!"
Koskovich observes:
"During a period when gender roles in French society moved from quite distinct to increasingly in flux, such performances were far from subversive; rather, by elaborately mimicking the dress, grooming, countenance, gestures, and forms of speech and singing attributed to the other sex, imitators reinforced normative gender expression. Comic representations of cross-dressing performed a similar function by making imperfect gender expression, notably the mixing of male and female conventions, into an object of mockery. "At the same time, at least some music-hall female impersonators—and perhaps many of them—apparently were homosexual in their off-stage lives. Given the close association of homosexuality and gender inversion during the era reflected in the collection, both the performances and their representation in postcard images may therefore have created coded spaces of sexual ambiguity for a select public that was in the know.”
The second major category of postcards are gallant visual narratives of women being wooed by other women dressed as men. Included are ten hand-colored postcards in a die-cut holder, titled "Les Cerises," Paris: Kunzli Frères, circa 1900. Koskovich suggests:
"The genre is no doubt related to the popularity of trouser roles in operettas and plays during the period; the celebrated actress Sarah Bernhardt, for instance, triumphed in several such roles, notably in a production of Shakespeare's Hamlet (1899) and in Edmond Rostand's L'Aiglon (1900). The link between the theatrical images and the gallant scenes is demonstrated by the music-hall and opera postcards in this collection that follow the conventions of the illustrated scenes; the only difference is that the performers are clearly identified. "Postcards of this type also may have constituted a mild and legally acceptable form of erotica calibrated for mass distribution. By portraying cross-dressed women in the sexual-aggressor role conventionally reserved for men and by tricking out the narratives almost invariably in the ancien régime trappings of the 18th-century, a period associated with libertine indulgence, the images likely offered inspiration for titillating fantasies of erotic role reversal. At the same time, any hint that actual women might behave with the masculine sexual agency represented in the postcards is neutralized by the coy and stylized poses; the historical settings; and the emphasis on carefully arranged theatrical backdrops, costumes and props.”
Lastly, one postcard is a reproduction of a comic drawing of a cross-dresser, and one is a comic photograph of a stout male villager dressed in the costume of a regional peasant woman.
Additional postcards (cards 81-207) include gallant scenes, humorous images, popular genre narratives, and additional promotional portraits of theatrical and music-hall male and female impersonators. One postcard portrays black performers. One series titled "Chasé-croisé" (circa 1900) depicts a gallant narrative with two female and two male characters; one of the two men is played by a man, the other by a cross-dressed woman. Three postcards are images from the Idylle a Trianon" series. Also included is a series of postcards depicting scenes from the life of Joan of Arc and several postcards from Swedish theater.
SOURCES
Osvaldo Sosa Cordero. Historia de las Varietes en Buenos Aires (Buenos Aires, Argentina: Corregidor, 1998).
"Courier des spectacles,"La Presse (Sept. 16, 1906); consulted May 5, 2011: http://gallica.bnf.fr/ark:/12148/bpt6k603870x.textePage.f2.langFR.
Henri Duvernois. "Vignt têtes sur deux épaules,"Je Sais Tout 4:6 (1908): pages 797–806.
Robert L. Herbert. Impressionism: Art, Leisure and Parisian Society (New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press, 1988): pages 115f.
Leonard C. Pronko. "Kabuki and the Elizabethan Theater,"in Samuel L. Leiter (ed.), A Kabuki Reader: History and Performance (Armonk, N.Y.: M. E. Sharpe, 2002): page 332.
[Eloi] Ouvrard. Elle est toute nue. La vérité sur la vie des coulisses, exposé par Ouvrard Père, ex-vedette des grands concerts de Paris (Paris: Au Café-Concert, 1926).
Martin Pénet, "Chansons Interlopes (1906–1966),"illustrated booklet included in the two-CD set Chansons Interlopes (1906–1966) ([Paris]: Labelchanson, 2006); album no. 001.
Bernard Savalle. "Henri Defreyn, acteur,"Le Cinema Français (website); consulted May 5, 2011: http://www.cinema-francais.fr/les_acteurs/acteurs_d/ defreyn_henri.htm.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Bertin, Robert.; Bloch, Jeanne.
Subjects:
France--Social life and customs.; Music-halls (Variety-theaters, cabarets, etc.)--France.; Sex in popular culture--France.; Transvestism--France.; Transvestites--France.; Theater--France.
Form and Genre Terms:
Postcards.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
NOTES
Collecting Program: Human Sexuality Collection.
"Female Impersonator" means the individual doing the impersonating is male and "Male Impersonator" means the individual doing the impersonating is female.
SERIES LIST
I. Music Hall and Theater Postcards
Music and Operetta
Cards 1-38, 81-102
Series II. Gallant Scenes of a Cross-dressed Woman Wooing another Woman
Cards 39-78, 103-152
Series III. Humor and Other
Costume Series
Historical Illustrations: Joan of Arc
Swedish Music Hall and Theater
Cards 79-80, 153-207
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Music Hall and Theater Postcards
  - Albertin célèbre imitateur, circa 1910; 1 (Folder 1)
    Performer: Albertin
    Medium: Black and white offset
    Impersonator: Female Impersonator
    Notes: Blank verso
  - [No Caption], circa 1910; 2 (Folder 1)
    Performer: Arigon
    Printer/Publisher: Der Artist
    Inscription: Arigon Imitateur
    Medium: Color offset
    Notes: Cherry pink on white cardstock. Divided verso; imprinted "Postkarte”.
  - Poilu's-Park. La Grande Divette. Le Poilu Bert-Gyll entre deux séjours aux tranchées de 1re ligne, circa 1915; 3 (Folder 1)
    Performer: Bert-Gyll
    Photographer: V. Lavaux
    Printer/Publisher: Luce Editeur
    Notes: French World War I soldier posed outdoors wearing a female gypsy costume. Divided verso; black rubber-stamp impression on verso: "Collection J.F.M.”
  - Poilu's-Park. Les Poilus Bert-Gyll et Mézy, duettists à transformation. Costumes de la Maison Granier. Guerre 1914–1915, 1915; 4 (Folder 1)
    Notes: The two cards offered here represent Poilu's Park, an amusement park for French and allied soldiers that operated from 1915 to 1916 in Commercy, 20 kilometers from the front in the Meuse. See the website maintained by the Inspection Adademique de la Meuse and other regional and national agencies: http://14-18.lecrivainpublic.net/scripts/travail.php?doc=442.
  - Bertin Imitant la Tortojada, circa 1907; 5 (Folder 2)
    Performer: Robert Bertin
    Medium: Black and white real photo
    Notes: Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating "Tous les pays étrangers n'acceptent pas la correspondance au recto. Se renseigner à la poste.”
  - Monsieur R. Bertin imitant Miss Clothilde Alégria, tireuse méxicaine, circa 1907; 6 (Folder 2)
    Notes: Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating "Tous les pays étrangers n'acceptant pas la correspondance au recto se renseigner à la Poste.”
  - Monsieur R. Bertin dans son imitation de Miette "La Cigale Parisienne"(Folies Marigny), circa 1900; 7 (Folder 2)
    Printer/Publisher: Monogram JD intertwined through an anchor
    Medium: Hand tinted offset
    Notes: Undivided verso imprinted "Ce coté est exclusivement réservé à l'adresse”
  - Monsieur R. Bertin imitant Yvette Guilbert (dernier genre), circa 1907; 8 (Folder 2)
    Photographer: A. E[illegible]
    Notes: Photographer's name partially legible (reproduction of embossing on original photo). Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating "Certains les pays étrangers n'acceptant pas la correspondance au recto se renseigner à la Poste.”
  - Mr Bertin. Imitation de Yvette Guilbert, circa 1907; 9 (Folder 2)
    Photographer: J. Bioletto
    City: Lyon
    Notes: Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating "Tous les pays étrangers n'acceptent pas la correspondance au recto. (Se renseigner à la poste"[final period and close parentheses missing in original].
  - Mr Bertin. Imitation de Mlle Foscolo excentrique, circa 1907; 10 (Folder 2)
  - Mr Bertin. Imitation de Mme Yvette Guilbert genre Pompadour, circa 1907; 11 (Folder 2)
    Notes: Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating "Tous les pays étrangers n'acceptent pas la correspondance au recto. (Se renseigner à la poste.)"
  - Mr Bertin. Imitation de la Belle Otéro, circa 1907; 12 (Folder 2)
  - Monsieur R. Bertin dans son imitation de l'excentrique "Polaire"(Folies Marigny), Postmarked 1904; 13 (Folder 2)
    Printer/Publisher: Monogram JD intertwined in an anchor
    Notes: Undivided verso.
  - Monsieur R. Bertin, imitant "La Tortojada"(Folies Marigny), Postmarked 1904; 14 (Folder 2)
  - Mr Bertin, circa 1910; 15 (Folder 2)
    Photographer: A. Espiugas
    City: Barcelona
    Notes: Divided verso; notice printed centered above line dividing message and address panels: "Tarjeta postal / Union postale universelle / España.”
  - Jeanne Bloch, circa 1910; 16 (Folder 3)
    Performer: Jeanne Bloch
    Photographer: Buger & Bert
    Printer/Publisher: F.C. & Cie.
    City: Paris
    Impersonator: Male Impersonator
    Notes: A comic actress who played both female and male roles in music-hall revues; dressed as a portly, gray-haired, bearded gentleman looking like then President of the French Republic, Armand Fallières. Card No. 308. Divided verso.
  - M. Defreyn (Sarah Yacco), Postmarked1903; 17 (Folder 3)
    Performer: Henri Defreyn (1878–1948)
    Photographer: G. Dupont
    Printer/Publisher: Le Carnet Mondain
    Notes: An operetta star who later developed a recording and film career. In the postcard offered here, Defreyn imitates Sadda Yacco (Kawakami Sadayakko; 1871-1946), a Japanese kabuki artist who performed to enthusistic audiences in Paris at the turn of the 20th century. Undivided verso.
  - Mr D'Hernonville. Homme Protée. Phénomène Vocal, circa 1904; 18 (Folder 3)
    Performer: D'Hernonville
    Notes: A noted music-hall "protean"performer who portrayed a series of female singing and speaking roles. Divided verso; imprinted at left on verso: "La Correspondance au recto n'est pas acceptée par tous les pays étrangers. (Se renseigner à la Poste.)”
  - Mr D'Hernonville imitateur, circa 1910; 19 (Folder 3)
    Photographer: R. Guilleminot
    Printer/Publisher: Boespflug et Cie
    Notes: Divided verso. On verso: Logo of a bridled horse head framed in a horseshoe.
  - Yvette Dolly, 1924; 20 (Folder 3)
    Performer: Yvette Dolly
    Photographer: Francis Photo
    Printer/Publisher: On verso: bri­dled horse head framed in a horse­shoe above a five-pointed star.
    Inscription: Moulin Rouge Paris 27/11/24 / A Myriam mon / bon souvenir / Dolly
    Notes: One tack hole each at upper and lower margin. Divided verso; black rubber-stamp impression on verso: "Collection J.F.M.”
  - Florin Imitateur, circa 1910; 21 (Folder 3)
    Performer: Florin
    Photographer: Louis Martin
    Notes: Divided verso
  - Florin Imitateur, circa 1910; 22 (Folder 3)
  - Florin Imitateur, circa 1910; 23 (Folder 3)
  - Fregoli nella Mimi, 1902; 24 (Folder 3)
    Performer: Leopoldo Fregoli (1867–1936)
    Printer/Publisher: Garzini & Pezzini
    City: Milan
    Notes: An internationally renowned Italian quick-change artist, Fregoli both sang and acted 20 or more characters in each of his shows. He made his first splash on the Parisian stage in 1900 and subsequently presented shows in the French capital that ran for up to a year. The two cards offered here present numerous vignettes showing poses and costumes from Fregoli's shows Mimi and Eldorado.
  - Fregoli nell Eldorado Quadro II, 1902; 25 (Folder 3)
    Notes: Undivided verso. Large "Carte Postale"followed by the term in other languages.
  - [Cricket on the Hearth], circa 1910; 26 (Folder 4)
    Performer: [Unidentified]
    Printer/Publisher: Ed. Lasseron
    City: Melun
    Inscription: Written in pencil on verso: Names of performers and the roles they are representing.
    Notes: Seven performers with both male and female cross-dressing standing on a lawn in front of a painted backdrop representing a bower. Based on the indication of the roles noted on the verso, the actors are appearing in a play based on the Charles Dickens novella The Cricket on the Hearth. Divided verso. On verso: Logo of a bridled horse head framed in a horse­shoe. Pale blue rubber-stamp impression on verso giving name and city of publisher.
  - Marthis ?? ..., circa 1910; 27 (Folder 4)
    Performer: Marthis
  - Maurice Homme Protée, circa 1907; 28 (Folder 4)
    Performer: Maurice
    Notes: Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating "Tous les pays étrangers n'acceptent pas la correspondance au recto (se renseigner à la poste)”
  - Maurice L'homme protée, circa 1910; 29 (Folder 4)
    Photographer: Bonfort
    City: Marseille
  - Novelty's imitateur à transformations, circa 1915; 30 (Folder 4)
    Performer: Novelty's
    Notes: Full length photo of a man in showgirl dress; vignette headshot of same performer in white tie. Divided verso.
  - M. de Sternac dans son imitation de Mme Yvette Guilbert, circa 1907; 31 (Folder 4)
    Performer: Fernand de Sternac
    Photographer: Cliché Le Ray, Montoire
    Printer/Publisher: Imprimeries Réunies
    City: Nancy
    Notes: Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating "Tous les pays étrangers n'acceptent pas la correspondance au recto (Se renseigner à la poste)"
  - M. de Sternac dans son imitation de Mme Sada Yacco, circa 1907; 32 (Folder 4)
    Photographer: Le Ray, Montoire
    Printer/Publisher: Imprimeries Reunies
  - [No Caption], circa 1920; 33 (Folder 4)
    Performer: Monté Verdi
    Photographer: Mce Boisdon
    Inscription: A Henri et / Gaston / délicat / souvenir / Monté Verdi
    Notes: Photographs by Maurice Boisdon, who specialized in theatrical and circus performers, cityscapes and landscapes.
  - [No Caption], circa 1920; 34 (Folder 4)
    Inscription: Du 18e au 20e Siècle
  - Louis Vernassier, l'homme protée musical dans son Travesti-dame, circa 1900; 35 (Folder 4)
    Performer: Louis Vernassier
    Photographer: Reutlinger
  - Louis Vernassier, l'homme protée musical excentrique dans son travesti-dame jouant: violon, manodline, mandole, violoncelle, piano, contrabasso, guitare, xylophone, grelots, saxophone, harpe, cuivres, etc. & tous instrument excentriques, circa 1907; 36 (Folder 4)
    Notes: Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating "Tous les pays étrangers n'acceptent pas la correspondance au recto (Se renseigner à la poste)”
  - Louis Vernassier protée musical excentrique dans son travesti-dame, circa 1910; 37 (Folder 4)
    Inscription: Written in black ink: Mes remerciements. Black rubber-stamp impression of signature: Vernassier L.
    Notes: Paired portaits of Vernassier in men's clothing and in costume as grand dame. Divided verso. Rubber stamp on verso: "Collection J F M”
  - [La Grammaire], circa 1910; 38
    Inscription: Written in pencil on verso: "La Grammaire"de Sabiche joué par les anciennes élèves de l'E P.S.
    Notes: Five young women in early 19th-century costume (three dressed as men) standing in a courtyard. Divided verso. Pink rubber-stamp impression on verso giving name and city of publisher. On verso: Logo of a bridled horse head framed in a horse­shoe.
  - [Black couple], circa 1900; 81 (Folder 10)
    Medium: Hand-Tinted Real Photo
    Notes: "Apparently a promotional photo for a music-hall act. Black couple with one man dressed in formal wear and one dressed in a flouncy gown, necklace and extravagant feathered hat (but no wig). The image introduces further confusion through swapping of highly gendered accessories: The man dressed as a man holds the woman’s fan, and the man dressed as a woman holds the man’s top hat. An exceptionally rare postcard—the only example I have documented of the genre representing black performers. Publisher’s monogram on recto. Circular rubber-stamp impression in pink ink on verso: “CARTES POSTALES DOCUMENTAIRES / 19___ / Collection Louis HESSENBRUCH / No____”. The 19 is followed by the numerals 55 written in black ink."
  - Les Fiancés, L'Abbé, circa 1910; 82-83 (Folder 10)
    Printer/Publisher: "Monogram JD intertwined through an anchor"
    Inscription: "Brief personal messages signed Félia."
    Medium: Black-and-White Printing (collotype)
    Notes: "Series of 2 postcards apparently showing the stars of a stage production, possibly an operetta, set in the 18th century. One shows a young woman dressed in the fancy garb of a male aristocrat, possibly an officer or court official, as she sports a sash. The other shows the same cross-dressed woman kissing a woman dressed in a summer gown and hat while a priest looks on in dismay. The caption indicates “L’Abbé — Oh! mais! oh! mais! Ils vont trop loin!” Stamp and postmark on recto."
  - M.R. Bertin. Le Celebre Imitateur Francais, circa 1907; 84 (Folder 10)
    Printer/Publisher: "Bauer Marchet et Cie"
    City: Dijon
    Notes: "Scarce bust-length portrait of Bertin in men’s clothing. Publisher’s name indicated in circular black rubberstamp impression on recto. Divided verso. Yellowing to varnish coating on recto; scattered spotting to verso."
  - Bertin, circa 1900; 85 (Folder 10)
    Photographer: Fialdo
    Notes: "Undivided verso imprinted “Tarjeta Postal / Union Universal de Correos / España / En e[s]te lado se escribe solamente la direccion” Hand-tinted in green with gold highlights. Foxing to verso."
  - "M. R. Bertin. Imitation de Mme Yvette Guilbert", circa 1907; 86 (Folder 10)
    Notes: "Publisher’s name indicated in circular black rubberstamp impression on recto. Divided verso. Yellowing to varnish coating on recto."
  - "M. R. Bertin. Imitation de Mlle LYDIA", circa 1907; 87 (Folder 10)
    Notes: "Publisher’s name indicated in circular black rubberstamp impression on recto. Divided verso. Remains of small rice-paper hinge on verso."
  - M. R. Bertin. Imitation de Mme OUVRARD, la Thérésa Moderne, 88 (Folder 10)
  - "Monsieur (et non Mademoiselle !) Thon Lind", Dated 1927; 89 (Folder 10)
    Performer: Thon Lind
    Printer/Publisher: "Alferocca Card No. 9344"
    City: Terni (Italy)
    Inscription: "Extended manuscript message on verso; no reference to subject of postcard."
    Notes: "Stamped and mailed in France. Last numeral of year on message and postmark somewhat unclear. Title, card number, publisher’s name and city printed in red on recto; publisher’s name and city also appear in tiny white letters at lower left in image. Short tear (2.25 cm) at lower margin."
  - "M. Pol Simon dans ses rapides transformations", circa 1904; 90 (Folder 10)
    Performer: Pol Simon
    Printer/Publisher: "Imp. M. Massenet"
    City: Chatillon
    Notes: "Divided verso; imprinted across top: “Carte Postale / La correspondance au recto n’est pas acceptée par tous les pays étrangers. (Se renseigner à la poste.)”"
  - La Tolosa, circa 1910; 91 (Folder 10)
    Performer: La Tolosa
    Notes: "Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating “La correspondance au verso n’est pas acceptée par tous les pays étrangers (Se renseigner à la Poste)” Small chip to one corner."
  - "Louis Vernassier l’homme-protéemusical- excentrique dans ses travesti-dame", circa 1910; 92 (Folder 10)
    Performer: "Louis Vernaissier"
    Notes: "Montage of three portraits of Vernassier showing his transformation from middle-aged man to grand dame. Divided verso; notice printed full width indicating “Carte Postale / La Correspondance au recto n’est pas acceptée par tous les pays étrangers. (Se renseigner à la Poste)”"
  - Louis Vernassier. L’Homme protée muscial dans son travesti dame, circa 1905; 93 (Folder 10)
    Photographer: R. Rivière
    City: Angers
    Inscription:
    Medium: Black-and-White Printing (collotype) Black-and-White Printing (collotype)
    Notes: Popular music-hall performer Louis Vernaissier, who played a wide variety of musical instruments while cross-dressed as a grand dame. Divided recto overprinted with a period promotional text for “A L’Entrée Libre,” a postcard shop in the working-class 12th arrondissement of Paris offering a “choix considérable de cartes postales” at 10 centimes each. Some wear and minor chipping to margins of recto.
  - Louis Vernassier. L’Homme protée muscial dans son travesti dame, postmarked 1910.; 94 (Folder 10)
    City: Angers.
    Medium: Black and white (collotype).
    Impersonator:
    Notes: Small chips (1 cm x 1 cm maximum) and tape mark to upper margin; stamp and postmark on recto. Louis Vernassier had a long and prolific career as a music-hall female impersonator whose act involved playing numerous musical instruments (this postcard lists 12 different ones, plus "tous les instruments excentriques"). This is one of the rarest of the several postcards representing Vernassier; I have seen only one other example (in a private collection in France).
  - L’Aiglon. Mme Sarah Bernhardt — Scène de Wagram, Postmarked 1902; 95 (Folder 11)
    Performer: Sarah Bernhardt
    Printer/Publisher: L.H.
    Inscription: Addressed to Mlle Marguerite Beaujean
    Notes: Black-and-white reproduction of a watercolor illustration signed Espinasse. Sarah Bernhardt (1844–1923) appearing in one of her most celebrated trouser roles as the son of Napoléon in L’Aiglon (1900) by playwright Edmond Rostand, who wrote the role for her. Undivided verso. Minor staining to upper margin of recto.
  - Jeanne Bloch, dans Armand’ retour de Londres. En Sca...là, j’marche, revue, circa 1910; 96 (Folder 11)